people say that success in trading is
20% skill and 80% psychology I don't
actually agree with that I think it's
different I've seen that success in
trading is mostly about the skill aspect
that being said I've also found that
well over 80% of the issues that people
have with their trading are
psychological but these are symptoms not
problems when you want to solve a
problem it's always best to look for the
root cause and in the case of trading
psychology issues the root cause is
usually to do with the skill itself if
you focus on fixing the skill issue the
psychological problems just disappear
they're often a byproduct of not
approaching the skill aspects correctly
so in this video I want to cover the
four most common or most challenging
psychological barriers that I've come
across I'll also give you a solution or
a prevention for each of them but it's
important to keep in mind that all of
these issues can be complex there could
be many different causes ways that they
manifest or Solutions but the solutions
that I'll give you are the ones that fix
them in most cases or at least go most
of the way to resolving them let's start
with the most obvious one and it's only
obvious because it's so common people
struggle with taking a loss and there
are many reasons for this so we all have
a cognitive bias known as loss aversion
in short this means that the pain of
losing is twice as powerful
psychologically as the pleasure of
gaining so we have a tendency to avoid
losses more than we seek gains but there
is a caveat here this is for situations
where we see there being gains and
losses and this is where a lot of people
go wrong with trading people have become
accustomed to viewing things as a matter
of winning or losing this applies to
Games sports business deals and many
other things that we can think of it's
all about winning or losing and losing
suggests failure but trading isn't about
winning or losing in fact it makes me
cringe when people refer to their
profitable trades as winning trades and
yes I've said it in the past as well but
I make a conscious effort not to anymore
successful trading is about having a
long-term positive Traders equation it
doesn't matter how many losing trades
you have what matters is that over time
your trading generates a positive output
from this equation and is repeatable let
me give you an analogy imagine we're
going to be flipping a coin and you know
the coin hasn't been tampered with so
there's a 50% chance of heads and a 50%
chance of Tails and I say to you if it
lands on heads you get $10 but if it
lands on tails you give me $5 and we can
play this game continuously until you
decide to stop so in that scenario how
would you feel when the coin lands on
tails and you have to give me $5 would
it bother you you probably wouldn't mind
at all you know that each coin flip has
a positive expectancy for you so the
more times we flip the coin the more
money you're likely to make overall it
doesn't feel like a loss when it lands
on Tails it's just part of the process
now let me ask you another question do
you know in that situation whether the
next coin flip will be heads or tails no
there's a 50% chance of each of them
happening you have no idea which one it
will be and the final question would
that fact bother you no because you
don't care what the individual result of
each coin flip will be you want to keep
flipping the coin because you have an
edge and this is the same with trading
we shouldn't be looking for so-called
profitable trade opportunities instead
we should be looking for trades where we
think it has a positive expectancy this
means when we assess the potential
positive and negative outcomes and their
probabilities we have a favorable
outcome overall let's say we're looking
at a trading opportunity and there's a
60% chance for a loss and a 40% chance
for a profit but the potential profit is
50 Pips and the loss would be 20 Pips do
we know what the outcome of that
individual trade will be no we just know
if we took that trade over and over
again or at least we think six times out
of 10 it would be a negative outcome and
four times out of 10 it would be a
positive one but we don't know what the
very next outcome of that individual
trade will be we're not fortune tellers
and it doesn't matter to us anyway if
it's a loss who cares as long as we keep
taking trades with a positive expectancy
like that we just need to keep flipping
the coin so there are two main things to
overcome this psychological barrier of
not wanting to take losses the first
thing is to stop thinking of individual
trades as winning or losing instead
reposition them as being part of a
longer term process and the second and
more important thing is to start
estimating the probabilities of your
opportunities the different outcomes
that could occur what are the
probabilities of them this way you can
figure out what the expectancy of the
opportunity is and over time you can
track the accuracy of your probability
estimates then go through a calibration
process to improve them and before we
move on just one more thing you can only
estimate the probabilities correctly if
your trading method detect something
meaningful in the markets like a change
in activity that lets you adjust your
estimates of the probabilities if it's
just based on nothing of course you're
not going to have any Edge and you know
whenever I talk about estimating
probabilities some people will complain
that it's not possible so firstly
Studies have shown that it is possible
to estimate the probabilities of future
outcomes and they also show that it's
possible to improve your accuracy and
this is something that we walk our
members through with great results but
if you don't consciously estimate
probabilities you're still doing it
subconsciously whenever you make
decisions anyway and this applies to
entering trades or assessing trade
opportunities or anything else in life
we're going through probability
estimates whether you realize it or not
when you trade you estimate
probabilities so I encourage you to make
it a conscious effort because that way
you can measure your accuracy and
improve on it and it may even reveal the
reason why you're not succeeding with
your trading as much as you'd like to
this next psychological barrier
manifests in many different ways just a
quick one before we continue if you want
more important insights to improve your
trading performance check out the Link
in the description box to my 1-hour
training I explain things that other
trading lessons never cover and these
are really critical for succeeding over
the long term with your trading career
so some of the more common ways are
hesitating to open trades reducing your
capital or getting nervous after hitting
a string of losses and closing trades
too soon these and many other problems
relate either directly or indirectly to
doubt and more specifically self-doubt
so let's go back to that coin flip
example from the previous point if we
were playing that game and you hit Tails
10 times in a row so you kept losing
money kept paying me that $5 but you
knew the coin was fair would you have
any doubts about flipping the coin again
no you know a losing streak will happen
based on probabilities but the expected
value of each coin flip hasn't changed
you still have the edge so you keep
playing you keep flipping the coin most
of the self-doubt that you experience as
a Trader simply comes down to not
knowing your Trad numbers you may think
you know your numbers but then you hit
some losses a losing streak or have a
period of uncertainty and it makes you
question everything you knew about your
trading and that's because most people
who think they know their numbers
haven't gathered them correctly or with
a big enough sample size and I spoke
about this in a previous video which
I'll link up here and I explained what
an appropriate sample size should be and
there are two things you can do to fix
this once again the first thing is to
focus on taking trading opportunities
with a positive expect y rather than
trying to decide if an opportunity will
be profitable or unprofitable now
there's another video I'll link up here
where I explained how this completely
changes the way that your brain
processes the situation it turns it from
an uncertainty to a risk and that means
less Reliance on emotion and
particularly fear so you process it in a
completely different way the second
thing is to invest your time into
collecting a big enough sample size to
be able to really rely on your trading
numbers and don't just focus on whether
you're profitable over a large sample
size also focus on things like the
accuracy of your probability estimates
and whether the opportunities you're
taking genuinely do seem to have a
positive expectancy and with both of
those points they're only going to be
dependable and meaningful if you have a
consistent approach that you use for
your trading otherwise each trade is
completely unrelated and your data as a
whole isn't going to give you any
confidence like if every trade is
approached in a completely different way
and you're only profitable overall
because you have a few lucky home runs
of course you're going to have some
doubts about your performance instead if
you approach your trading in a
consistent way and you have positive
numbers from an appropriate sample size
this removes the self-doubt almost
completely of course some people have
self-doubt in general due to low
self-esteem perhaps from past traumas
but this is the psychological part then
that needs to be solved and isn't
related to the skill aspect but for most
people it's the skill aspect and the
points that I've provided should prevent
or solve this for you everyone always
focuses on how difficult it is to deal
with losses most trading psychology
videos or lessons are about the losing
side but I've been involved in the
markets for over 20 years and I've taken
some huge losses even six figure losses
at some points and I can tell you from
my experience and from what I've seen
from other successful Traders the most
psychologically difficult part has been
dealing with profits in fact here's a
clip from the legendary Trader Andy ker
saying pretty much the same thing now
what happens dollar Yen Now crashes off
to 130 and my op options are now worth
2% I made 20 times my money what do I do
that's the hard part of money management
because when a position goes against you
if I have a spot position it goes
against me I have a stop loss it's easy
I'm out but managing profits is hard
because you have to manage your you have
to manage your psychology you have to
manage your expectations you have all
this ego stuff that starts to Bubble Up
I've seen many Traders I've hired many
many many Traders over the years and
some of them couldn't they couldn't deal
with profit it's above a certain level
this leads to people closing profitable
trades way too soon or way too late like
I explained in this video up here most
Traders end up feeling frustrated with
almost every trade because they measure
themselves against the perfect exit and
this then creates L lose situations for
them but there is some good news for you
as you get more experienced and
profitable trades aren't such a surprise
for you anymore they do become easier to
deal with but as I said focusing on the
skill aspects can solve most trading
psychology issues and this is no
different so how can we solve this issue
through improving our trading skills now
I'm going to sound like a broken record
but it's all about the expectancy of the
opportunity you'll notice this come up
time and time again I stress it so often
because I hardly ever see Traders
talking about probabilities but it's
only by estimating probabilities that
you have any idea at all whether your
decisions are the right ones to take
this is the key skill that Traders need
to develop so think about your Trading
how are you currently deciding when to
exit a profitable trade is it when it
hits your target is it when it struggles
at a key level of some sort is it when
you've made a certain amount of money or
maybe it's just based on a gut feeling
or something like that I believe it
should be by analyzing the potential
next outcomes and assessing the
expectancy of the situation from that
point onwards just like I think you
should do with your trade entries so
this means that you should continue to
actively analyze the markets after
entering a trade to anticipate and
assess the next potential price
movements then the changes in expectancy
will dictate whether it's no longer
viable to keep the trade open or when
the expectancy dropped enough that it's
still viable to keep it open but maybe
time to take a partial close and scale
out of the trade or in some situations
it might even be that the Situation's
improved and it's time to scale into the
trade you know here's something that I
think is really important I advise you
to stop thinking of trading as being
completely different to anything else to
any other fields instead look for
similar similarities with other fields
think about the way that experts or the
really top performers in other fields
would make decisions and what role their
analysis would play in that process it
should be focused on the expected value
this takes the guesswork and the
psychological aspects out of this
decision to exit a trade or not there
are two broad areas where we see this
psychological barrier the first is with
your development as a Trader and the
second is with your individual trades so
let's start with your development many
Traders are short-term focused with
their progress they want to be
profitable with their trading yesterday
and they're not willing to wait to
achieve their goals so as a result they
try to FasTrack themselves to live
trading and then they beat themselves up
when they're not achieving the profits
that they expected and there are many
causes for this but two big ones are
unrealistic expectations and a lack of
clarity over your development process
the unrealistic expectations are
unfortunately a byproduct of the culture
online particularly on YouTube and
social media if many flashy trading
gurus are promoting how quickly and
easily they became profitable and Rich
that's going to impact your own
perceptions about your progress likewise
if these people are constantly talking
about monthly double or even triple
digit percentage returns you'll feel
like an underachiever until you reach
that and that's not really something
realistic to achieve on a regular basis
if it was all those people would be
billionaires so you need to look at
trading as a profession as simp as
people make it sound it's actually a
complex skill and there are many
individual skills that you need to
develop to succeed at it so just like
any other difficult profession it takes
time to learn you wouldn't expect to
start a degree in engineering and be in
a top level job earning megabuck after 6
months from starting it's no different
from trading it takes time of dedicating
yourself to learning the skill before
you start earning good money from it
many people think that rushing your way
to profit in the live markets will help
you reach your goal goals faster but
it's actually more likely to slow you
down or even reverse your progress in
fact most of the members that we have at
wo are people who started off learning
elsewhere and they'll often say how
they've wasted so much time chasing this
instant success that other people were
promoting wasting months or years going
through funding challenge after funding
challenge only to realize that actually
they needed to develop their skill
further first and that time could have
been spent on that instead and this does
actually relate to the second point
which is having no ity over your
development process so Traders are often
working forwards towards their goal of
becoming profitable essentially they
learn the basic skill and then think
okay what's next and then what's next
and what's next kind of like trying to
find your way through the wood without
anything to guide you it's like okay do
I turn left or right here now what left
or right instead it's a much better idea
to start from the end and work backwards
to think about what you're trying to get
to and what skills you'll need to be
consistently profitable or whatever else
and then think one one step backwards
from there what would be the final thing
you're working on before becoming
consistently profitable how long would
that take given the time that you have
available to work on your trading then
what about one step back from there and
so on and so on essentially you want to
figure out the major Milestone goals
that you need to achieve on route to
being profitable with your trading then
figure out the stepping stone goals that
you need to work on on a daily basis to
achieve each of those milestones and
this will give you much more clarity
over exactly what you need to do and how
long it may take then you just focus
relentlessly on the next Milestone goal
and the individual actions that you need
to take to get there and don't get
distracted by the end goal just one
Milestone at a time listen I think it's
great to have a sense of urgency with
your development or your work in general
it's something I try to encourage my
team to have this feeling of urgency but
this should manifest with you taking the
right actions each day with intensity it
shouldn't be causing you to look for
shortcuts or trying to rush your
progress this ends up happening when you
feel like you're falling behind some
arbitrary deadline or goal that doesn't
really need to be there now I first
started learning about the markets in
2002 firstly focused on investing and
later on trading and I went fulltime
with my trading in 2012 that's 10 years
later I'm not sure exactly at what point
I would have been considered
consistently profitable it's not like
you wake up one day and suddenly you
realize you've done it but I can tell
you for sure it wasn't anything less
than six or seven years afterwards
started now I'm not saying it will take
you that long hopefully it won't I was
young and naive I made tons of mistakes
doing things the hard way but hopefully
that gives you more perspective I can
tell from our analytics on YouTube that
the largest part of our audience is male
below the age of 25 and those are the
years as a man where you feel like
everything needs to happen instantly but
as you get a bit older as you hit your
30s and so on you begin to realize that
things just take time and if you focus
on doing things the right way regardless
of how long they take you're actually
more likely to reach your goal in a more
efficient way I always think of it like
running a marathon so imagine you want
to improve your marathon time what would
be the right strategy to take would it
be to try and Sprint right from the
start of course not but that's how a lot
of people are approaching their trading
development instead the better way is to
think about the entire journey and work
backwards from there find where there
could be efficiencies or improvements
that could speed things up essentially
you want to work on finding the pace
that ensures you do reach the Finish
Line that's the first priority and then
figure out how to go faster without
compromising that so when it comes to
trading it should be focused on actually
reaching the goal and then start
thinking about where you can make things
more efficient rather than sprinting
your way there and burning out or not
reaching it at all and then we come on
to the next part of short-term Focus
which is about the individual trades now
as I've mentioned earlier in this video
too many Traders feel like like their
performance lives and dies on each
individual trade they take Extreme
Measures to try and make sure each trade
is a profit they hold on to losing
trades too long they move their stop-
loss and they take their profits too
early and ultimately these actions may
increase the chance of that individual
trade being a profit but that comes at a
cost these actions may actually be
negatively affecting your long-term
Traders equation so although you get
that dopamine hit from an individual
profit your long-term performance is is
likely to be negative as a result of
that instead you should be entering and
managing trades while keeping your
long-term performance in mind thinking
about how the actions you're taking will
impact your Traders equation overall if
you deviate from your plan on an
individual trade what will that mean if
the same situation played out a 100
times how are your actions affecting the
probabilities or the potential future
profit and loss that I believe is the
key to successful trading executing each
individual trade in the most optimal way
but but in line with what will lead to
good long-term performance and in some
cases that means taking a loss on an
individual trade rather than taking
actions that expose you to more risk you
know people get instant gratification
from the outcomes of individual trades
but you need to find a way to condition
yourself so that the instant
gratification is attached to taking
actions that benefit your long-term
Traders equation so hopefully you can
see the recurring themes and the things
that I'm explaining to you I don't care
about short-term success I care about
sustainable long-term lasting success
and you should as well the right way to
go is focusing on things like
probabilities and the Traders equation
and following plans that increase the
probability of succeeding over the long
term rather than just the ones that will
maybe get you there quicker I know some
of you or most of you will disregard all
of what I'm saying some people hate it
when I'm realistic and conservative
because it feels like I'm dampening your
hopes and dreams you know I'm not here
to teach you how to gamble but people
want the racy Flash exciting stuff I'm
here to help you succeed and hopefully
if just one of you takes on board the
things that I'm saying from over 20
years in the trenches then I'll be happy
with this video so if you made it this
far I think you also deserve to know the
truth about emotions in trading when you
look at the science behind it you
realize that most trading psychology
advice is completely wrong so you can
find out the truth in this video here